[Music]
how much exercise is too much there
doesn't appear to be any studies on the
longevity of marathon or Triathlon
Runners but this study in which more
than a thousand joggers were followed
for up to a dozen years is able to offer
some insight surprisingly the light
joggers appear to have the lowest
mortality rates moderate joggers had a
worse mortality rate than light
joggers they still did better than that
of sedentary non- joggers but strenuous
joggers did not there wasn't a
significant difference in death rates
between those jogging more than four
hours a week and those not jogging at
all so the death versus jogging
intensity graph was a U-shaped curve
with the lowest mortality bottoming out
among those taking it relatively easy
clocking 1 to 2.4 hours a week over no
more than 3 days at a slower average
pace so more may not necessarily be
better the jogging study spurred
sensationalist headlines like fast
running can kill but the strenuous
joggers were just dying at a higher rate
compared to light joggers not compared
to the general population of non-
joggers here's what a metaanalysis found
of all such similar studies yes
diminishing returns but the only clear
mortality bump was associated with
inactivity however there was a
retrospective analysis of more than a
thousand male Olympic track and field
athletes that suggested that those who
had extraordinary early Peak Performance
had lifespans shortened by almost 5
years the regimen for Peak Performance
may not be the same as that for Optimum
Health and Longevity perhaps the Mantra
exercise is medicine metaphor should be
taken a step further recognizing that
like any powerful medicine there may be
a safe range of
dosing
[Music]